Finding Aid for the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee Records LSC.0107
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Materials Concerning Defendants
  - Correspondence from "the boys" to Alice Greenfield., 1943 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letter, 1943 July 11, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Parra updates Alice on how the "boys" are doing in San Quentin.
    - Letter, 1943 June 16, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Reyes Salazar make reference to the recent Zoot Suit riots and how they might affect the case of the Sleepy Lagoon defendants.
    - Letter, 1944 February 29, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letter, n.d., San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif., undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Letter from Rodman asking Alice to send him a picture of a "chick", preferably of her, to put up on his wall.
    - Letter, 1943 September 24, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Letter from Chepe letting Alice know how he is doing.
    - Letter, 1944 May 4, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Chepe writes of the appeal and of what his plans are if it isn't successful.
    - Letter, 1943 April 28, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Manny lets Alice know how he is doing in San Quentin.
    - Letter, 1944 June 7, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Chepe writes of his distress over the news of the invasion of France.
    - Letter, 1944 January 25, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      "Smiles" writes Alice about the disappointment the "boys" feel over the postponement of the appeal.
    - Letter, 1944 September 8, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Chepe writes of his concern over the possible outcome of the forth coming appeal. He asks Alice to send his regards to the "boys" in Chino.
    - Letter, 1943 January 13 to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Leyvas writes of his disappointment over the outcome of the trial and thanks Alice for her hard work and friendship.
    - Letter, 1943 April 11, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letter, 1944 August 14, Los Angeles, Calif. to Manuel Delgado (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letter, 1944 May 18, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Chepe Ruíz writes to Alice about his visit with his mother.
    - Letter, n.d., San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif., undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Bob writes Alice about some of the "boys" being transferred to Chino.
    - Letter, n.d., San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif., undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Victor asks Alice to send him photographs of girls so that he can draw them.
    - Letter, 1943 July 12, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letter, 1943 April 10, San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield and the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Letter to the editor of The Appeal News.
    - Letter, n.d., San Quentin, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif., undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Bob asks Alice to thank their supporters including Anthony Quinn.
    - Statistics: the nature of the Mexican American criminal, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Ayers, of the Los Angeles County Sheriff's Foreign Relations Bureau, wrote this controversial report on the "biological and racial nature" of violence among Mexicans and Mexican Americans.
    - Letter, 1944 March 12, Chino, Calif. to Alice Greenfield, Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      "Smiles" Parra writes Alice to let her know how much better the situation is at Chino.
  - Correspondence from "the boys" to various persons., 1944 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Information regarding defendants. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Including carbon copies, photostats, mimeographed, holograph, typescript, biographies and reports of "the boys."
  - Miscellaneous releases, letters, etc. concerning the Sleepy Lagoon case and the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee., (9 items). (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Not from or by the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee.
  - Newsclippings about the case. Various papers., (7 items). (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Materials Gathered by the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee Regarding Minorities - Emphasis is on Los Angeles Mexican Minority Issues
  - Los Angeles County Grand Jury., October 1942; (11 items). (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Includes correspondence, reports from the Los Angeles Police Department and findings of the Grand Jury.
  - Mexican "boy gangs" of Los Angeles., (16 items). (Box 4, Folder 8)
    "Pachuco" situation.
  - Mexican juvenile delinquency in Los Angeles., (54 leaves) Photostats of clippings. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    UNAVAILABLE for use.
    - Delinquency in wartime, 1942, 1943, or 1944 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Holton was Chief Probation Offiicer, Los Angeles County Probation Department. In this report he discusses the then current level of juvenile delinquency in Los Angeles County and the fallacy of increased juvenile delinquency amongst Mexican American youth. Suggests changes and additions in social service programs for minority youth.
  - Mexican minority in Los Angeles., (13 items). (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Includes Waxman's letter.
  - Mexican minority - General., (8 items). (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Sinarquismo., (4 copies). (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Translation of 24 page booklet.
- Miscellaneous Material Collected by the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee Concerning Minorities, Labor, etc.
  Available on microfilm reel 3.
  - The Americas - A Review of Latin American News. Bulletin. vol.2 no.6 to vol.2 no.21., (January 4, 1944 to September 5, 1944); (17 items). (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correo de Norte - Publicado pro El Consejo pro Democracia Panamericana., February 4, 1944 to August 30, 1944; (12 items). (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Council for Civic Unity., (34 items). (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - International Labor Defense., (18 items). (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Correspondence and miscellaneous file mainly concerning the Sleepy Lagoon Case.
  - International Labor Defense., Legislative and Information Service (Bulletin) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - International Labor Defense., News (July 2, 1943 to September 2, 1944). (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous printed publications., (9 items). (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous printed publications., (14 items). (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Fraternidad; Año I, Num. 6, 1944 November (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Editorial applauding the outcome of the Sleepy Lagoon trial appeal and the reversal of the convictions. Congratulates the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee for all of the hard work done on behalf of the defendants, two of whom were Mexican citizens.
  - Miscellaneous materials., (16 items). (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Posters, fragments, clippings, etc.
  - Miscellaneous mimeographed material collected by the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Photographic Plates, Newspaper Mats (Box 6)
- The San Quentin News., (Folder). (Box 12)
  vol.5, no.45-49; vol.6, no.1-19 (December 21, 1945 to July 5, 1946).
- Transcript of the Trial
  - The people of the state of California, plaintiff and respondent vs. Gus Zammora [sic], et. al defendents and appellants: reporter's transcript on appeal., October 13-December 10, 1942; Digitized microfilm of the trial transcript.
  - The people of the state of California, plaintiff and respondent vs. Gus Zammora [sic], et. al defendents and appellants: reporter's transcript on appeal., October 13-December 10, 1942; 6032 leaves in 12 volumes. (Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10)
    Original transcripts in boxes 7-10 are RESTRICTED from access and UNAVAILABLE for use due to their fragile condition. However, photocopies of the originals have been made and are available to the public.
    - The people of the state of California, plaintiff and respondent, vs. Gus Zammora [sic], et. al, defendants and appellants: reporter's transcript on appeal, 1942 October 13 - 1943 March (Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10)
      At head of title: "In the Superior Court of the State of California in and for the County of Los Angeles, Department 43, Hon. Charles W. Fricke, Judge."
      "No. 90344."
      "E.R. Perry and G.J.Kennelly, Official Reporters."
      CONTENTS:
      v. 1. Index; [trial date:] Tuesday, October 13, 1942 ([7], 1-515 leaves)
      v. 2. Thursday, October 22, 1942 (leaves 516-1004)
      v. 3. Tuesday, October 27, 1942 (leaves 1005-1515)
      v. 4. Friday, October 30, 1942 (leaves 1516-2046)
      v. 5. Thursday, November 5, 1942 (leaves 2047-2540)
      v. 6. Tuesday, November 10, 2942 (leaves 2541-3002)
      v. 7. Monday, November 16, 1942 (leaves 3003-3550)
      v. 8. Thursday, November 19, 1942 (leaves 3551-4040)
      v. 9. Wednesday, November 25, 2004 (leaves 4041-4537)
      v. 10. Wednesday, December 2, 1942 (leaves 4538-5067)
      v. 11. Monday, December 7, 1942 (leaves 5068-5510)
      v. 12. Wednesday, December 10, 1942 (leaves 5511-6032)
      - vols.1-3 (Box 7)
        Volume 1, October 13, 1942.
        Volume 2, October 22, 1942.
        Volume 3, October 27, 1942.
      - vols.4-7 (Box 8)
        Volume 4, October 30, 1942
        Volume 5, November 5, 1942
        Volume 6, November 10, 1942
        Volume 7, November 16, 1942
      - vols.8-9. (Box 9)
        Volume 8, November 19, 1942.
        Volume 9, November 25, 1942.
      - vols.10-12. (Box 10)
        Volume 10, December 2, 1942.
        Volume 11, December 7, 1942.
        Volume 12, December 10, 1942.
        Volume 12, December 10, 1942. Second copy (last 100 leaves only).
- Legal Documents
  Available on microfilm reels 7-8.
  - Appellants' Opening Brief., (2 copies). (Box 11)
  - Application for Leave to File Brief as Friends of the Court and Brief., (2 copies). (Box 11)
    - Application for leave to file brief as friends of the court and brief: the Sleepy Lagoon case, 1944 May 15 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Carey McWilliams, Clore Warne, A. L. Wirin, Aubrey Grossman, Attorneys for Applicants; Vito Marcantonio, David Scribner, William Standard, Nathan Witt, of the New York Bar; Sol. D. Kapelson, of the New Jersey Bar, of Counsel.
      Appendix A: Excerpts from report entitled "Statistics" be Ed. Duran Ayres, Foreign Relations Bureau (sheriff's office).
      Appendix B: Excerpts from the San Quentin News, November 25, 1943, article entitled "The Neutral Corner."
  - Clerk's transcript., (2 copies). (Box 11)
  - Decision of District Court of Appeal. (Box 11)
  - The People vs Zammora., pp.219-288. (Box 11)
- Scrapbook
  Available on microfilm reel 8.
  - 1 Scrapbook. (Box 12)
  - Newspaper: Daly News H.F.O. 'This is the story of crime', 1942 (Box 12)
  - 3 "Zoot Suit" posters - World Premiere Season 1978-1979. Mark Taper Forum Music Center. (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous Items
  - Receipts, envelopes, ledger leaf and distribution list for Mystery., 12 items. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Ledger of expenses and donor contributions., October 1943-December 1944.; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Print of Sleepy Lagoon Defendants Leaving the Hall of Justice, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains one 13 x 10.25 print.